Guide to the Student Volunteer Movement for Foreign Missions Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
- Conventions, Series VIII
  The earliest quadrennial conventions were held in February or March, but, beginning with the Rochester gathering of 1909/1910, the pattern was established to hold the meetings shortly after Christmas, extending a day or two into the new year. Attendance at the conventions rose dramatically from 680 present at Cleveland in 1891 to 6890 present at Des Moines in 1919/ 1920. Reflecting the general fortunes of the Movement and national economic conditions, attendance then dropped steadily to slightly over 2000 at Indianapolis in 1935/1936, the last convention sponsored solely by the SVM. Beginning with Toronto in 1939, the conventions were sponsored by the SVM, the YMCA and YWCA, denominational student organizations and the Canadian Student Christian Movement. The conventions were progressively of a more consultative or educational nature, focusing on the problems of the general missions enterprise rather than on the work of the Student Volunteer Movement. The conventions were ostensibly student gatherings, but at Kansas City (1913/1914), for example, nearly one-third of the delegates present were not students.
  The first convention at Cleveland in 1891 was the largest student conference to its time. More than any of the later gatherings, the first convention was a propaganda exercise for the Movement, an attempt to publicize its aims and work. By the third convention, again held at Cleveland in 1898, the Movement had established its reputation and could speak to wider issues; seven addresses on the program, for example, were devoted to the problem of financing the missionary enterprise. At the Nashville convention 1906, another issue came to the fore, the relationship of the missionary enterprise to international relations; addresses such as "The Relation of the Student Volunteer Movement to International Comity and Universal Peace" were on the program. Beginning with the Rochester convention of 1909/1910, gusts of the new trend in missions theory were felt; Sherwood Eddy's opening address was entitled "Is our Christianity Worth Propagating?" At Kansas City in 1913/1914, two Christian nationals, rather than Western missionaries, presented the needs of China and Japan at the convention.
  The Des Moines convention of 1919/1920 was a watershed for the Movement. Many student delegates were dissatisfied with the dogmatic tone and narrow focus of the convention. As the Harvard University Crimson reported after the convention: "Men looked forward to a discussion of broad religious problems with their economic and political bearings. What they got for the most part from the speeches in the big Colosseum was narrow sectarian religion."("The Des Moines Convention", Harvard University Crimson, January 7,1920.) At the conventions which followed, measures were taken to meet the criticisms voiced at Des Moines, both in terms of the content of the message being presented and the format for presenting it. The Indianapolis convention of 1923/1924 is the first for which extensive files are available in the Student Volunteer Movement archives. Three major issues were addressed by the convention: industrial conditions overseas, race relations, and hopes for lasting international peace. After the presentation of these issues on the first day of the convention, fortynine discussion groups under student leadership were formed. The trend toward student leadership and participation was continued at Detroit in 1928 as thirty-three "colloquia" were formed, with adults serving in a "resource person" capacity only. The trend toward a broader conception of missions was also continued, as evidence by the reaction of one conservative Kentucky coed: "The reports of the convention that I have both read and heard indicate that the spirit of the recent Detroit Convention was not only modernistic and unscriptural but also Bolshevistic."(Quoted in Weyman C, Huckabee, "History and Significance of the Student Volunteer Movement for Foreign Missions", p. 94.)
  Despite these efforts toward a new style in the SVM conventions, criticisms similar to those heard at Des Moines persisted. Seminar leaders at the Indianapolis convention of 1935/1936 echoed familiar themes in evaluating the convention:
  If the platform speakers could attend the seminars and could thus find out what the student needs are, their later platform addresses would be more helpful.
  Platform addresses were by speakers marked by too much age and maturity.
  Program was not so much above heads, nor under heads, but beside the heads of the students-did not come to grips with student needs.(SVM Archives, Series VIII, Indianapolis 1935/1936, "Evaluations and Criticisms.")
  The 1939 convention at Toronto represented a radical departure from the patterns of the past. It was the first of the conventions to be held on a university campus rather than at a large city hotel or hall. The conference was billed as a consultative meeting with attendance limited to 500 students. It was jointly sponsored by the SVM, National Intercollegiate Council, Student Christian Movement of Canada, and Commission on University Work of the Council of Church Boards of Education. Students and campus study groups were asked to prepare papers in advance of the conference which were to serve as the basis of discussion for seminar groups. The 1943 Student Planning Conference on the World Mission of the Church held in Wooster, Ohio was similar to the Toronto conference.
  With the Second World War having ended and American campuses being infused with new religious life, the massive SVM convention pattern of the past was revived at the University of Kansas in Lawrence in 1947/1948 and 1951/1952. The 15th Quadrennial Convention of the SVM, again sponsored in conjunction with other movements, was billed as the North American Student Conference on Christian Frontiers (FRONCON) and attracted over 2500 delegates. There were also echoes of former controversies over the relationship of the Church's world mission to international relations. After conference chairman Congressman Walter N. Judd of Minnesota voiced the opinion in his opening address that the United States government should send aid to the Chinese nationalist government of Chiang Kai-shek, a protest movement among the student delegates arose. A letter appearing in the Daily Froncon, the conference newspaper, included the statement: "As a group of students interested in the welfare of this conference, the undersigned wish to express concern over the note of international power politics that had been sounded here and with the apparent identification of the Christian Church with one side in such politics."("Tempest on Christian Front Over Judd Stand at Lawrence", Topeka Kansas Capital, December 31, 1947.) Student Volunteer Movement General Secretary Winburn Thomas's response to the controversy was: "This is a missionary conference and we have no desire to turn it into a political sounding board."(Ibid.)
  There are over forty linear feet of records related to the quadrennial conventions in the SVM archives. The earlier conventions are documented primarily by scrapbooks containing newspaper clippings and reports. Extensive files for each conference beginning with Indianapolis 1923/1924 are divided according to topical categories. Of particular interest among these rough divisions are 1) the "budget and finance" categories which document how convention funds were
  - Oversize Record Books
    - Toronto, 1902 (Box Ov1)
    - Nashville, press clippings, 1906 (Box Ov8)
    - Nashville, press clippings, 1906 (Box Ov2)
    - Rochester, press clippings from Rochester papers, 1909-1910 (Box Ov7)
    - Rochester, press clippings from Rochester papers and non-Rochester papers, 1909-1910 (Box Ov14)
    - Kansas City, press clippings from Kansas city papers, 1913-1914 (Box Ov14)
    - Kansas City, press clippings from secular papers, 1913-1914 (Box Ov6)
    - Kansas City, press clippings from religious papers, 1913-1914 (Box Ov1)
    - Indianapolis, press clippings, 1923-1924 (Box Ov17)
    - Indianapolis, minutes of committees, 1922-1924 (Box Ov6)
    - Detroit, press clippings and memorabilia, 1927-1928 (Box Ov14)
    - Detroit, press clippings, memorabilia, minutes, 1927-1928 (Box Ov4)
    - Detroit, memorabilia, 1927-1928 (Box Ov8)
    - Detroit, registration records, 1927-1928 (Box Ov9)
    - Detroit and Buffalo, registration fee journal, 1927-1932 (Box Ov7)
    - Buffalo, press clippings and memorabilia, 1931-1932 (Box Ov4)
    - Buffalo, memorabilia, 1931-1932 (Box Ov2)
  - Cleveland (1891)
    - Delegates (Box 559, Folder 6555)
  - Detroit (1894)
    - Program (Box 559, Folder 6556)
    - Convention report (Box 559, Folder 6557)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 559, Folder 6558)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 559, Folder 6559)
    - Press releases (Box 559, Folder 6560)
  - Cleveland (1898)
    - Press releases, publicity (Box 559, Folder 6561)
    - Scrapbook: press clippings (Box 559, Folder 6562)
  - Toronto (1902)
    - Convention report (Box 559, Folder 6563)
    - Executive committee (Box 559, Folder 6564)
    - Mott, Mrs. John R. (Box 559, Folder 6565)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 559, Folder 6566)
    - Press releases/publicity (Box 559, Folder 6567)
    - Prayer topics (Box 559, Folder 6568)
  - Nashville ( 1906)
    - Convention report (Box 559, Folder 6569)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 559, Folder 6570-6571)
  - Rochester ( 1909-1910)
    - Convention report (Box 559, Folder 6572)
    - Executive committee (Box 559, Folder 6573)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 559, Folder 6574)
    - Speakers (Box 559, Folder 6575)
  - Kansas City (1913-1914)
    - "Delegates' Handbook" (Box 559, Folder 6576)
    - Scrapbook on exhibits on missions (Box 560, Folder 6577)
  - Des Moines (1919-1920)
    - Convention report (Box 560, Folder 6578)
    - Daily bulletin (Box 560, Folder 6579)
    - Delegates: promotion (Box 560, Folder 6580)
    - Delegates: quotas (Box 560, Folder 6581)
    - Executive committee (Box 560, Folder 6582)
    - "Honor Roll of Deceased Missionaries" (Box 560, Folder 6583)
    - Literature (Box 560, Folder 6584,6585)
    - Mott, John R. (Box 560, Folder 6586)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 560, Folder 6587)
    - Organization (Box 560, Folder 6588)
    - Press clippings (Box 560, Folder 6589,6590)
    - Program (Box 560, Folder 6591)
    - Scrapbook of the convention exhibits on missions (Box 560, Folder 6592)
  - Indianapolis (1923-1924)
    - Agenda (Box 561, Folder 6593)
    - Budget and finance: budget (Box 561, Folder 6594)
    - "The Christian Enterprise Abroad" (Box 561, Folder 6595)
    - Committee on Arrangements (Box 561, Folder 6596)
    - Convention report (Box 561, Folder 6597)
    - Convention report (Box 561, Folder 6598)
    - Correspondence: miscellaneous (Box 561, Folder 6599,6600)
    - Delegates (Box 561, Folder 6601)
    - Delegates: accommodations (Box 561, Folder 6602)
    - Delegates: promotion (Box 561, Folder 6603)
    - Delegates: registration (Box 561, Folder 6604)
    - Evaluations and criticisms (Box 561, Folder 6605)
    - Executive committee (Box 561, Folder 6606,6607)
    - Exhibits (Box 561, Folder 6608)
    - "Five Years of Christian Co-operation in China" (Box 561, Folder 6609)
    - Literature (Box 561, Folder 6610)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 561, Folder 6611)
    - Preparation committee (Box 561, Folder 6612)
    - Press releases, publicity (Box 561, Folder 6613,6614)
    - Printed material: miscellaneous (Box 561, Folder 6615)
    - Program (Box 561, Folder 6616)
    - Quadrennial Committee (Box 561, Folder 6617)
    - Speakers: Church and Local (Box 561, Folder 6618)
    - Scrapbook: miscellany (Box 561, Folder 6619)
  - Detroit (1927-1928)
    - Advance preparation (Box 561, Folder 6620)
    - Agenda (Box 561, Folder 6621)
    - "Call to Prayer" (Box 561, Folder 6622)
    - Budget and finance: Accounts payable vouchers (Box 561, Folder 6623)
    - Budget and finance: bank accounts (Box 562, Folder 6624)
    - Budget and finance: check vouchers (Box 562, Folder 6625)
    - Budget and finance: fund raising (Box 562, Folder 6626)
    - Budget and finance: invoices, freight bills, etc. (Box 562, Folder 6627)
    - Budget and finance: petty cash (Box 562, Folder 6628)
    - Buttons, badges, etc. (Box 562, Folder 6629)
    - Colloquia (Box 562, Folder 6630)
    - "Comments, reports, suggestions from letters and editorials" (Box 562, Folder 6631)
    - Committee on Arrangements (Box 562, Folder 6632)
    - Convention report (Box 562, Folder 6633)
    - "Daily Bulletin" (Box 562, Folder 6634)
    - Delegates: accommodations (Box 562, Folder 6635)
    - Delegates: minority (Box 562, Folder 6636)
    - Delegates: promotion (Box 562, Folder 6637)
    - Delegates: registration (Box 562, Folder 6638)
    - Delegates: transportation (Box 562, Folder 6639)
    - Denominational meetings (Box 562, Folder 6640)
    - Literature sales (Box 562, Folder 6641)
    - Press releases/publicity (Box 562, Folder 6642)
    - Printing blocks (Box 562, Folder 6643)
    - Program (Box 562, Folder 6644)
    - Quadrennial Convention Committee (Box 563, Folder 6645)
    - Theological Seminaries (Box 563, Folder 6646)
    - Scrapbooks: Comments, reports, and suggestions; Suggestions to future officers and committees by Corilla Brodnax (2 copies) (Box 563, Folder 6647)
  - Buffalo ( 1931-1932)
    - Ackley, S.A. (Box 563, Folder 6648)
    - Agenda (Box 563, Folder 6649)
    - Book exhibit (Box 563, Folder 6650-6652)
    - Booths (Box 563, Folder 6653)
    - Boy Scouts (Box 563, Folder 6654)
    - Budget and finance: bank accounts (Box 563, Folder 6655)
    - Budget and finance: expenses (Box 563, Folder 6656)
    - Budget and finance: financial reports and statements (Box 564, Folder 6657)
    - Budget and finance: fund raising (Box 564, Folder 6658-6666)
    - Budget and finance: pledge cards (Box 565, Folder 6667-6668)
    - Budget and finance: registration fees (Box 565, Folder 6669)
    - Budget and finance: registration fees, refunds (Box 565, Folder 6670)
    - Buffalo churches (Box 565, Folder 6671)
    - Buffalo paper no. 2: "A Short Course of Reading" (Box 565, Folder 6672)
    - Buttons, badges, etc. (Box 565, Folder 6673)
    - "Call to Prayer" (Box 565, Folder 6674)
    - Clerical assistance (Box 565, Folder 6675)
    - Convention report (Box 565, Folder 6676)
    - Convention report orders (Box 565, Folder 6677)
    - Complimentary tickets (Box 566, Folder 6680,668l)
    - Correspondence: colleges and universities (Box 566, Folder 6678,6679)
    - Correspondence: colleges and universities (Box 566, Folder 6682-6685)
    - Delegates (Box 566, Folder 6686)
    - Delegates: accommodations, hotels (Box 566, Folder 6687)
    - Correspondence: colleges and universities (Box 567, Folder 6688-6692)
    - Correspondence: miscellaneous (Box 567, Folder 6693)
    - Delegates: accommodations, hotels (Box 567, Folder 6694)
    - Delegates: accommodations, private homes (Box 568, Folder 6695)
    - Delegates: accommodations, restaurants (Box 568, Folder 6696)
    - Delegates: promotion (Box 568, Folder 6697)
    - Delegates: applications for credentials (Abel - Zigler) (Box 568, Folder 6698-6700)
    - Delegates: applications for credentials: (by schools) Canada (Box 568, Folder 6701)
    - Delegates: applications for credentials: (by schools) Alabama - New Jersey (Box 568, Folder 6702-6704)
    - Delegates: foreign (Box 568, Folder 6705)
    - Delegates: promotion (Box 568, Folder 6706)
    - Delegates: Methodist (Box 568, Folder 6707)
    - Delegates: minority (Box 568, Folder 6708)
    - Delegates: registration and credentials (Box 569, Folder 6709-6711)
    - Registration and credentials, special concessions (A - Z) (Box 569, Folder 6712,6713)
    - Delegates: registration packets (Box 569, Folder 6714)
    - Delegates: special (Box 569, Folder 6715)
    - Delegates: statistics (Box 569, Folder 6716)
    - Delegates: substitutions (Box 569, Folder 6717)
    - Delegates: transportation (Box 569, Folder 6718)
    - Delegates: transportation (Box 570, Folder 6719)
    - "Delegates' Handbook" (Box 570, Folder 6720)
    - Denominational meetings (Box 570, Folder 6721)
    - Entertainment (Box 570, Folder 6722)
    - Evaluations and Criticisms (Box 570, Folder 6723)
    - First Aid (Box 570, Folder 6724)
    - Library exhibit (Box 570, Folder 6725)
    - Meeting facilities (Box 570, Folder 6726)
    - Miscellaneous typescript material (Box 570, Folder 6727)
    - Motion pictures (Box 570, Folder 6728)
    - Pageant (Box 570, Folder 6728)
    - Press releases/publicity (Box 570, Folder 6730,6732)
    - Printing (Box 570, Folder 6731)
    - Printed material: publications (Box 570, Folder 6733)
    - Quadrennial Convention Committee (Box 570, Folder 6734)
    - Quadrennial Questionaire (Box 570, Folder 6735)
    - Quadrennial Questionaire (Box 571, Folder 6736)
    - Round Tables (Box 571, Folder 6737)
    - Speakers (Box 571, Folder 6738,6739)
    - SVM General Council (Box 571, Folder 6740)
    - "Where Buffalo Worships" (Box 571, Folder 6741)
    - Young Peoples' Meetings (Box 571, Folder 6742)
    - Bound volume: Delegate registration (Box 571, Folder 6743)
    - Bound volume: Verbatim transcript of proceedings (Box 572, Folder 6744)
  - Indianapolis (1935-1936)
    - Records of delegate registration (cards)
    - College students; by institution (Canada; Alabama - Iowa) (Box 573)
    - College students; by institution (Nevada - Wyoming) (Box 574)
    - Mission board secretaries; foreign missionaries; YMCA secretaries; all others (Box 575)
    - Numerical order (118-2299)
    - Records of delegate registration (cards)
    - Numerical order (2300-3269) (Box 576)
    - Numerical order (3270-4269) (Box 577)
    - Numerical order (4270-7271) Seminar preference cards; by name of delegate (A - C) (Box 578)
    - Seminar preference cards (D - Z) (Box 579)
    - Engraved blocks for publicity printings Portraits (A - F) (Box 580)
    - Engraved blocks for publicity printings Portraits (G - M) (Box 581)
    - Engraved blocks for publicity printings Portraits (P - W) (Box 582)
    - Scrapbooks and bound volumes
    - Application blanks; non-collegiate delegates (Box 583)
    - Delegate registration by institutions (Box 584)
    - Hotel assignments transcript of proceedings (Box 585)
    - Agenda (Box 586, Folder 6745)
    - Announcements (Box 586, Folder 6746)
    - Archbishop of York (Box 586, Folder 6747)
    - Bibliography (Box 586, Folder 6748)
    - Book exhibit (Box 586, Folder 6749)
    - Booths (Box 586, Folder 6750)
    - Budget and finance (Box 586, Folder 6751)
    - Budget and finance: bank accounts (Box 586, Folder 6752)
    - Budget and finance: expenses (Box 586, Folder 6753-6755)
    - Budget and finance: financial reports and statements Ill (Box 586, Folder 6756)
    - Budget and finance: fund raising (Box 586, Folder 6757)
    - Budget and finance: insurance (Box 586, Folder 6758)
    - Budget and finance: miscellaneous (Box 586, Folder 6759)
    - Budget and finance: registration fee refunds (Box 586, Folder 6760-6763)
    - Buttons, badges, etc. (Box 587, Folder 6764,6765)
    - Christian Mission in World Perspective (Box 587, Folder 6766)
    - Clerical assistance (Box 587, Folder 6767)
    - Cleveland invitation (Box 587, Folder 6768)
    - Convention center material (Box 587, Folder 6769)
    - Convention report (Box 587, Folder 6770)
    - Correspondence: Colleges and universities (AL - IL) (Box 588, Folder 6771-6773)
    - Correspondence: Colleges and universities (IL - ND) (Box 588, Folder 6774-6780)
    - Correspondence: Colleges and universities (OH - WI; Canada) (Box 589, Folder 6781-6786)
    - Correspondence: delegates (A - F) (Box 589, Folder 6787,6788)
    - Correspondence: delegates (G - Z) (Box 590, Folder 6789-6792)
    - Correspondence: miscellaneous (Box 590, Folder 6793-6796)
    - Correspondence: miscellaneous 6SO4,6SO5 Delegates: accommodations, hotels (Box 591, Folder 6797-6799)
    - Correspondence: Student Christian Movement of Canada (Box 591, Folder 6800)
    - "Daily Bulletin" (Box 591, Folder 6801)
    - Delegates (Box 591, Folder 6802, 6803)
    - Delegates: accommodations, hotels (Box 591, Folder 6804, 6805)
    - Delegates: accommodations, hotels (Box 592, Folder 6806)
    - Delegates: accommodations, restaurants (Box 592, Folder 6807)
    - Delegates: applications for credentials (A - W) (Box 592, Folder 6808, 6809)
    - Delegates: entertainment (Box 592, Folder 6810)
    - Delegates: foreign (Box 592, Folder 6811)
    - Delegates: promotion (Box 592, Folder 6812-6815)
    - Delegates: promotion (Box 593, Folder 6816)
    - Delegates: promotion reports (Box 593, Folder 6817)
    - Delegates: registration and credentials (Box 593, Folder 6818, 6819)
    - Delegates: registration packet (Box 593, Folder 6820)
    - Delegates: special (Box 593, Folder 6821,6822)
    - Delegates: transportation (Box 593, Folder 6823)
    - "Delegates' Handbook" (Box 593, Folder 6824)
    - Denominational meetings (Box 593, Folder 6825)
    - Evaluations (Box 593, Folder 6825A)
    - Exhibits (Box 593, Folder 6826)
    - Exhibits: Methodist (Box 593, Folder 6827)
    - Exhibits: projects (Box 594, Folder 6828,6829)
    - Exhibits: projects (China) (Box 594, Folder 6830)
    - Exhibits: projects (Box 594, Folder 6831)
    - Exhibits: Wesley Fellowship in Japan (Box 594, Folder 6832)
    - First Aid (Box 594, Folder 6833)
    - (Indianapolis) Cleveland paper no. 1 (Box 594, Folder 6834)
    - Indianapolis paper no. 2: "Programs, speakers, costs, book, a call to prayer" (Box 594, Folder 6835)
    - Indianapolis paper no. 3: "Speakers, Leaders, Seminars" (Box 594, Folder 6836)
    - Indianapolis paper no. 4: "Quotas, costs, transportation" 6g3g Indianapolis paper no. 5: "Program features" (Box 594, Folder 6837)
    - Interviews (Box 594, Folder 6839)
    - Library Exhibit (Box 595, Folder 6840-6843)
    - Location Search (Box 595, Folder 6844)
    - Meeting facilities (Box 595, Folder 6845)
    - Miscellaneous typescript materials (Box 595, Folder 6846)
    - Mott luncheon (Box 595, Folder 6847)
    - Motion pictures (Box 595, Folder 6848,6849)
    - Music (Box 595, Folder 6850)
    - Music (Box 596, Folder 6851)
    - New Year's Eve Party (Box 596, Folder 6852)
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 596, Folder 6853,6854)
    - Notes: SVM Staff (Box 596, Folder 6855)
    - Pageant (Box 596, Folder 6856,6857)
    - Peace controversy (Box 596, Folder 6858)
    - Periodical exhibit (Box 596, Folder 6859)
    - Photographs, drawings (Box 596, Folder 6860)
    - Photographs: unidentified (Box 596, Folder 6861)
    - Preparation committee (Box 596, Folder 6862)
    - Preparation committee (Box 597, Folder 6863,6864)
    - Preparation committee: ideas (Box 597, Folder 6865,6866)
    - Press Bureau (Box 597, Folder 6867)
    - Press releases/publicity (Box 597, Folder 6868-6870)
    - Press releases/publicity; mailing lists (Box 597, Folder 6871)
    - Printed material; misc. (Box 597, Folder 6872)
    - Printing (Box 597, Folder 6873)
    - Printed material: official (complete) (Box 598, Folder 6874,6875)
    - Race controversy (Box 598, Folder 6876)
    - Seminars (Box 598, Folder 6877-6880)
    - Seminars: notes (Box 598, Folder 6881)
    - Seminars: notes (1A - 29 except 9, 13, 14,16, 20, 27) (Box 599, Folder 6882-6888)
    - Seminars: notes (30 - 33) (Box 600, Folder 6889,6890)
    - Speakers (Box 600, Folder 6891-6895)
    - Speakers: church and local (Box 600, Folder 6896)
    - Teas (Box 600, Folder 6897)
    - Theme and objectives (Box 600, Folder 6898)
    - Ushers (Box 600, Folder 6899)
    - Volunteer workers (Box 601, Folder 6900)
    - "A World-Wide Christian Outlook" (Box 601, Folder 6901)
  - Toronto (1939-1940)